Inventory of the Theodocius Joshua Scurlock Papers 1855-1888
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Theodocius Joshua Scurlock Papers, 1855-1888.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. 81 Scu4
116 items.
Letters, 1855-1888, received by or concerning Dr. Theodocius Joshua Scurlock while a resident of Texas and Mexico from family members in Alabama and Texas and friends in Alabama, Mississippi and Texas. Also includes a diary, December 1867-April 1869, kept by Scurlock on his journey to Mexico.
Theodocius Josha Scurlock.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift 04/00/1981.
Scope and Content Information
The collection is primarily composed of letters received by Dr. Theodocius Joshua Scurlock (1828-1887), a graduate of Tulane University and a resident of Texas and Mexico, 1855-1888, from family members in Alabama and Texas, and friends in Alabama, Mississippi, and Texas. The letters reflect the restlessness of the pre-Civil War years, and the difficulties and disillusionment felt by many people during Reconstruction. Diary included was kept by Scurlock on his journey to Mexico, December 1867-April 1869, in which he gives his impressions of the people he encountered as well as the natural history of the regions he passed through.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection has been organized into 5 Series: 1. Letters, 1850-1859, 2. Letters, 1860-1869, 3. Letters, 1870-1879, 4. Letters, 1880-1889, 5. Letters, no date.
Arrangement
The letters in this collection are arranged into Series by ten year incriments, the Subseries are then arranged chronologically into individual years. Not every year produced letters and this is reflected in overall arrangement. The diary is listed separately as the last item in the collection.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Reconstruction.
Geographical Names:
Texas--History--1846-1950.; Mexico--History--1867-1910.; Alabama--History--1819-1950.; Mississippi-- History.; Mexico--Description and travel.
Components List
  Series 1: Letters, 1850-1859
- Letters, 1850-1859., 50 items. (Box-folder 1:1-5)
  - Letters, 1855., 16 items. (Box-folder 1:1-2)
    - Lucena Scurlock, Macon County, Alabama, to son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] [Pittsburg, Texas], 14 January 1855., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Glad to have received letter but worried about health; reports brother Dan had left for Irving [College]; money hard to come by and price for cotton very low; refers to pending lawsuit; other family news.
    - Lucena Scurlock, Macon County, Alabama, to her son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], [Pittsburg, Texas], 5 March 1855., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Worries about health and relates deaths of various towns people; money hard to come by and business bad; other family and town related news.
    - Lucena Scurlock, Macon County, Alabama, to her son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], [Pittsburg, Texas], 16 April 1855., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Crops doing well; received letter from a most "dangerous woman," claiming son hadn't paid a debt; advises him to stay away from this "awful woman"; mentions pending lawsuit referred to as "hooke suit" (?); other family and town news.
    - Augustus Darby, "Lockland" [Macon County,] Alabama, to T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, [Pittsburg, Texas], 3 May 1855., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Refers to a favor which "came to hand"; talks about crops and prices; refers to the burning of a foundry in Montgomery [Alabama]; many suffering from scarlet fever; mentions the Hook's lawsuit being taken to Supreme Court; other family and town news.
    - Lucena Scurlock, Macon County, Alabama, to her son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], [Pittsburg, Texas], 12 June 1855., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Complains about mail system; has not received any letters from son; crops doing very well, especially corn; discusses Hook's lawsuit; relates town "anicdote"; other family news.
    - Elisa C. Scurlock, "Lockland, [Macon County], Alabama, to brother, [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], Pittsburg, Texas], 1 July 1855., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Glad to receive letter after "too months"; crops doing very well; Scarlet fever still "going through neighbourhood"; other family news.
    - Lucena Scurlock, Macon County, Alabama, to her son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], [Pittsburg, Texas], 2 July 1855., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Speaks of fine crops and many deaths from Scarlet fever; Hook suit not yet decided; advises to stay away from the "slandering living old devil" who claims he hasn't paid debt; other family news.
    - Lucena Scurlock, Macon County, Alabama, to her son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], [Pittsburg, Texas], 13 July 1855., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Worried that lawyers want evidence from him for Hook's case; advises not to give any at all; reports crops are good except cotton and all are well.
    - Lucena Scurlock, Macon [County], Alabama, to her son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], [Pittsburg, Texas], 23 July 1855., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Reports a retrial for "Hooke's" case and advises that he give no evidence; advises to stay away from "Tom the big baby"; asks him not to mention case in any letters except to her, Mit or Will; other family news.
    - S.G. Jones, Laplace, Alabama, to T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, [Pittsburg, Texas], 17 Aug. 1855., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Replies to question about health and crops; gives long account about political opinions relating to the "American party", break up of the Whigs and strengthening of Democrats; relates local arrests; business interests shifting; other news about common friends.
    - Lucena Scurlock, Macon County, Alabama, to her son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], [Pittsburg, Texas], 3 Sept. 1855., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Disease going around caused by snakes, many deaths; defines Hook's case as divorce case; advises to not give any evidence; case has been given a retrial; worried about Mary's [sister] health; not receiving Texas paper; other family news.
    - D[an] Scurlock, Irving College, to brother T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, [Pittsburg, Texas], 15 Sept[ember] 1855. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Received letter; has severe cold, health at Irving generally good; plans on staying two years; has not rained lately and is very warm; Had sent catalogue, will send another.
    - James G. Henderson Binetree P.O. Ups[h]ur County, Texas, to [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] [Pittsburg, Texas], 24 Sept. 1855., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Requests help in getting into business as an "averseer."
    - James G. Henderson, Pinetree, Texas, to Theodocius Joshua Scurlock, [Pittsburg, Texas], 11 Oct. 1855., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Inflicted with typhoid, hopes to be well soon; asks that Scurlock take care of some business dealings; received letter from William Harrison giving news of many deaths in Montgomery, County [Alabama]; provides arrangements for moving [to Texas]; family news.
    - D[an] Scurlock, Irving College to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock],n.p., 2 Dec. 1855 [?]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Times dull as session ending; has sprained ankle; has received letter from Ma which criticizes his spelling; will try again to send catalogue.
    - Lucena Scurlock "Lockland", Macon County, Alabama, to her son T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, [Pittsburg, Texas], 16 Dec. 1855., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Sends papers on Freeman Divorce case; refers to a petition and preparation of legal papers; other family news.
  - Letters, 1856., 12 items. (Box-folder 1:2-3)
    - D[an] Scurlock, Irving College, to his brother T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, [Pittsburg, Texas], 8 January 1856., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Relates how letter had been detoured to mother's house, was "read at home" then sent on to Irving; advises T.J. to settle down and get married; also advises to not travel until decision to make Kansas a state is made; advises to go to Kansas if it becomes a slave state; mentions a planned act of violence by Negroes near Clarksville [Tennessee] on the Cumberlan[d] River; planned to knock us all in the head" and "make themselves free Ladies and Gentleman."; other family news.
    - G[reen] B. McNiel Phila[delphia] Neshoba County, Mississippi to T[heodocius] Josh[ua] Scurlock [Pittsburg, Texas], 18 February 1856., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Glad to hear that he is happy, expected him to be "Alabama-sick" [homesick]; has begun farming, finds its hard work; all in good health except mother who has "posey "; other news.
    - Green B. McNiel, Philadelphia, Nesh[oba County] Miss[issippi] to his friend [Theodocius] Josh[ua Scurlock] [Pittsburg] Texas. 26 April 1856., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Complains in great length that Josh did not stop to visit on his way to Texas; glad to hear his health has improved with the "Minreul wutter"; inquires about a Negro, John, who held freedman's status; other family news.
    - S. G. Jones, Laplace [Alabama] to T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock [Pittsburg, Texas], 18 May 1856., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Relates the marriage of two couples of the area; reports the results of the elections for probate and circuit judge and refers them to their respective parties; have had long dry spell, hasn't been good for the "God of Macon...King cotton"; reports other deaths and gives some family news.
    - Lucena Scurlock, Macon County Alabama, to her son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], 12 June 1856., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Bill has gotten married, spends great deal of time telling why he shouldn't have "don[e] the deed"; begs son not to go to Central America because climate not good for health; crops are doing well except cotton; inquires about "Ben's wife" who was lost on a boat which was sunk on 20 April 1856; has hired new help who is young and "don't know much"; other family news.
    - D[an] Scurlock, Irving College to brother T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock [Pittsburg, Texas], 18 June 1856., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Gives long philosophical and metaphorical arguments about the importance of good health; compares the "excruciating pain" of the invalid to the "vast freedom" of the healthy; will remain at College for 6 week break in isolation as few students have remained.
    - M.D. Brackmon Henderson, Rusk County Texas, to Mr. T. Thetford, Marshall [County, Texas], 20 July 1856., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Refers to a debt owed by Mr. Scurlock and to Mr. Scurlock's absence at this time; mentions a hired black man in the employ of Mr. Scurlock.
    - Mr. [?] Rockmore Henderson [Rusk County Texas] to Mr. [T.] Thetford, n.p., 6 Oct. 1856., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Has not heard or seen [Theodoicus Joshua] Scurlock nor has he been in [Texas]; Has not the funds to pay the debt but will soon; refers to a boy [slave] who "has plenty to eat but nothing to do."
    - Mary Darby, Macon County, Alabama, to her brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], 6 Oct. 1856., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Pleads with brother to stop his traveling, to buy a home and settle down; claims that hundreds of tears have been shed, thinking he was dead; begs [T.J.] to meet brother Billy in Marshall [Texas] and stay with him.
    - [Lucena Scurlock], Macon County, Alabama, to her son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] [Sulphur Springs, Lampassas County Texas], 6 Oct. 1856., 4 pages. 2 cys. of AL. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Glad to receive letter and that he [T.J.] hasn't gone to Nicaragua; sorry to learn he has been "lying on the bed of affliction"; encourages him to go to Marshall [County, Texas] to meet [brother] Bill who has just married; sister has been married; sent 2 letters to different addresses; other family news.
    - R.W. Montgomery, Webberville Travis county, Texas to T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, 30 November 1856. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Rejects Scurlock's proposition to buy his land in Nepsher County; would like $3 an acre; doesn't believe land in that area is selling for less.
    - C.A. Laughlin, Austin City, Texas to his friend [Theodocius Joshua] Scurlock, New Orleans, [Louisiana ], 15 Dec. 1856., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Hopes business better for Scurlock than himself; selling out and moving to New Orleans; enjoyed traveling from his town.
  - Letters, 1857., 10 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - C.A. Laughlin, Shreverport, Louisiana, to friend [Theodocius Joshua] Scurlock, n.p., 3 March 1857., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Has returned to "this city" and plans to say; is pleased by the business prospects; believes could make good profit on investments; likes the amusements of the city.
    - Lucena Scurlock, "Lockland" [Macon County] Alabama, to her son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 5 April 1857., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Has not received word in 3 months; very cold weather and is affecting the crops; very little corn; money is tight; has bought "a negro"; had poor crop last year; other family news.
    - S.G. Jones, Cross Keys, Macon [County] Alabama, to T[heodocius J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 3 May 1857., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Has had a "very cold and backward spring"; 200 deaths since Xmas from measles; brother is talking about joining U.S. Army; Democrats have full ticket for legislature and County offices; many old whigs have gone Democrat; Democrats only party "able to beat back abolitionists and save our country from ruin"; reports Freeman and Williams lawsuit decided in favor of Williams; other family and town news.
    - Thomas Harbison, Macon County, Alabama, to friend [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 14 June 1857., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Relates family is well, brother Dan is home from Tennessee, brother William had measles; will try to visit [T.J.] and that part of country; a few deaths have occurred caused by measles; other town news.
    - G[reen] B. McNiel Philad[elphia], Neshoba County, Mississipppi to his friend [Theodocius] Josh[ua] [Scurlock], n.p., 16 July 1857., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Glad to have received letter; sorry Josh didn't come to visit; crops doing badly because of cold spring but should make profit in cotton; voted for Buchanan in election as did Josh.
    - D[an] Scurlock, Tuskegee [Alabama] to his brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 11 Aug. 1857., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      In good health; has been trying to find a job; reading law now; married an unnamed woman; crops okay except cotton for which it has been too cold.
    - S.G. Jones, "Lockland" Macon County, Alabama to T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 30 Aug. 1857., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Glad to receive letter and all in good health; American Party has won full representation in both Houses of Congress; describes political antics of both parties concerning "burying" the opponent; crops doing well except cotton because of cold; relationship between Jones family and Scurlocks not on firm ground as a result of daughter Mit's husband; other town news.
    - Lucena Scurlock, "Lockland" [Macon County] Alabama, to son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 18 Sept. 1857., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Has not been well but glad to receive letter; crops not very good, cotton getting a high price, about 15 cents; Wishes he could come to visit before she dies; discourages [Josh] to go to Central America as there will be "fighting enuf [sic] to do in your own native land."; other family news.
    - D[an Scurlock], Tuskegee [Alabama], to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 30 Sept. 1857., ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Has a slight cold; have been several weddings; thinking about going to law school in Tennessee; would like to set up practice in Texas or "other new country,"; other family news.
    - Thomas S. Cliett, Macon County, Alabama, to T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Cubahatched P.O. [Texas], 1 November 1857., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Has the "clap", likes T.J.'s proposition, would like to be doing something; hard times coming on; other family news.
  - Letters, 1858., 11 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
    - D[an] Scurlock, LaPlace, Alabama, to his brother T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 5 Feb. 1858., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Just returned home; has a cold; expenses for trip amounted to $60, Did not need money advanced by T.J.
    - William M. Johnston, Marshall, Texas to T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 20 Feb[uar]y 1858., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Has on hand $150 belonging to T.J. received through money order; Mr. Barker has paid nothing on debt; sister sends word T.J. must get married.
    - G.B. McNiel, Philadelphia, Neshoba County Miss[issippi] to [Theodocius] Josh[ua] Scurlock, 7 March 1858., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Misses Josh very much, encourages him to come and visit several times; family is well; has been married; other family news.
    - Dan Scurlock, "Lockland" [Macon County Alabama,] to brother T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 21 Apr. 1858., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Has received no word since February; refers sarcastically to Cupid and Social Life; reading [law] at home; intends to come to Texas following winter; other family news.
    - D[an] Scurlock, LaPlace [Alabama] to brother T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 5 May 1858., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Describes the fashions of LaPlace and the young ladies; crops doing well, plenty of food; convention meeting in Montgomery [Alabama] to discuss dissolving of nation; court system inefficient and overloaded; other family and town news.
    - G.B. McNiel, Philadelphia, Neshoba County Miss[issippi] to Friend [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 2 June 1858., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Surprised to hear he is studying medicine although thinks he's too old; married a 45 year old man to his first wife, thought that was strange; has been very ill with chills and fever; crops not very good, winter was too wet.
    - D[an] Scurlock, "Lockland" [Macon County] Alabama, to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], 13 July 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Describes in detail the "examinations" which were attended by all the music lovers; loves young America; still plans to go to Texas to live, would like to practice law there; sister is living in unfortunate situation; encourages him to study medicine; other family news.
    - N.D. Ward, Marshall, Texas to [Theodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 29 July 1858., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Requests to have bond signed, money given and note returned, in reference to Hart Conyer.
    - N.D. Ward, Marshall, Texas to T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 18 August 1858., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Has received signed note; rejects offer to sell piece of land to a friend because terms are too long for the low price offered.
    - Lucena Scurlock, Alabama, to her son [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 1 Sep[tember] 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Has been ill for 10 days; advises him to not go to New Orleans too early because of Yellow fever; encourages him to write to brother [Dan] to go to law school in Montgomery; other family news.
    - D[an] Scurlock, n.p. to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 1 Sep[tember] 1858., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      All in good health; have been a few cases of Typhoid fever; crops very good; has been reading [law], feels this year has been a waste, will go back to read [with another lawyer] as before; other family news.
  - Dan Scurlock, LaPlace [Alabama] to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 1 December 1859., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Ma has decided to move to Polk County Texas; requests a small house; this has foiled plans for school, will maybe farm in Texas if can't find a school.
  Series 2: Letters and Papers, 1860-1869
- Letters and Papers, 1860-1869., 38 items. (Box 1-2)
  - Letters, 1860, 20 items. (Box-folder 1:6-7)
    - W. Carrie, Pittsburg [Texas?] to [?], Feb. 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Receipt for $287.50 included; speaks of terms of payment; refers to an unknown lawsuit; has a jug of whiskey and no one to drink it with.
    - Dan Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant [Texas] to his brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 23 March 1860., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Has made business contacts requested; the due bill has come up in court but they cannot collect on it; and other family news.
    - Thomas Harbison, Polk County, Texas to friend T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 24 May 1860., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Land sold to Day and Thompson for $3 an acre; brother William left for Alabama; corn looks good but cotton is small, haven't had rain since 16 of April; other town news.
    - Dan Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant, [Texas] to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 31 May 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Discusses recent emigration to Texas of family and friends from Macon County Alabama; presents some prejudices toward northwesterners; refers to a note coming due; crops good but need rain; refers to the "railroad sensation" in Jefferson which will take some time to settle; other family news.
    - Thomas Harbison, Polk County Texas, to T[heodocius] Josh[ua] Scurlock, n.p., 22 June 1860., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Speaks of crops and lack of rain; reports problems with child slave Scurlock left [to his brother]; other family news.
    - Dan Scurlock Mt. Pleasant [Texas] to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 3 July 1860., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Making preparations from 4th of July Celebration; have had little rain and temperatures have been up to 98 [F.]; has heard of yellow fever in T.J.'s city, advises him to take care of himself; refers to the drinking habits of friends.
    - T[obias] G[ibson] Richardson, Louisville, [Kentucky] to [Theodocius Joshua] Scurlock, n.p., 3 July 1860., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Instructions referring to Scurlock moving out of the house he is living in and what the owner expects will be done by Scurlock in upkeep.
    - G[reen] B. McNiel. Phila[delphia], N[eshoba] C[ounty], Mississippi, to friend [Theodocius] Josh[ua Scurlock], n.p., 29 July 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Family all well; had intended to move to Texas but crops failed, will have to buy corn this year; anxious to see Josh, wants to know why he hasn't married.
    - Dan Scurlock Mt. Pleasant [Texas] to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 4 August 1860., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Weather has been very hot, have had no rain, crops are burning, cotton failing, wonders if Texas is "a fit place for civilized men to live", many Western town and private homes have been burned because of the abolition movement, "The people are aroused to a sense of their [the abolitionist's] danger", compares it to Harper's Ferry; refers to T.J.'s thesis, suggests the topic of Tetanus, mentions a case of murder Dan is defending; centering on a Negro who contacted tetanus after a severe whipping.
    - William Gardner, Pittsburg, Upshur [County] Texas to [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 24 August 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Inquires about a note for several hundred dollars that he has heard nothing about, would like to know what happened to it; shows his discontent with Texas, describes it as "this land of contention where belzebub seems to be prime ruler."
    - G.B. McNiel, Phila[delphia] Nes[hoba] County, Miss[issippi] to friend [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] [New Orleans, Louisiana ], 29 August 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)